hi and welcome to this GrandMA 3 tutorial this
is episode 2 and it's about patching your first
fixtures in the last episode we took a tour around
the software we looked at all the different fixed
system views and we looked at where these
views are located on the real console
we also looked at navigating the on pc software
with all the different system views and we took
a tour at the rear of the console with all
the different connectors in the back if you
missed that episode click here in the corner
and that will take you right to that episode
in this episode we are patching fixtures
into the desk for the first time
to be able to make views later as you can see
here in the presets pool we can't make any presets
right now and that's because we have to patch
some fixtures into the GrandMA 3 console first
the reason for this is that some of
the views we need position, color, beam
etc first becomes available when
you have some fixtures in the patch
and the option will be different depending on what
type of fixture you patch this is different from
the GrandMA 2 where you were able to make all your
views on a blank console with a new show loaded
before we dive in if you get any value out of
these videos please consider liking the video
and subscribing to the channel so you don't miss
any new episodes in the future and if you have any
questions along the way please leave a comment
below and i'll answer them as well as i can so
let's dive in in order to start patching fixtures
we start by navigating to the small cog icon on
the console here you'll find a lot of different
options and we will definitely visit this place
in later tutorials because this is where a lot of
different settings are controlled and manipulated
navigate to the patch and press it this opens
up the patch on the GrandMA 3 console if you're
used to GrandMA 2 consoles we have to approach
patching in a different way that we're used to
on the GrandMA 2 console you would start by
creating a line inside that line you would choose
a fixture type and then patch it the lines gave
us a good overview of all our different fixture
types and it made it easy to find fixtures you
needed if you wanted to change something later
in the GrandMA 3 software things have changed
a little these lines are gone and now you can
make a patch directly in one large pool you now
have the option of grouping your fixtures but you
have to do it manually let's first patch some
fixtures and then look at grouping let's go to new
fixture and click here on insert new fixture you
can right click on new fixture or you can click on
insert new fixture both will open up this window
in this window you will have multiple options
option 1 in current show this will show you what
fixtures you're using in your show but in this
case we haven't patched any fixtures yet so it's
going to be empty option 2 is GrandMA 3. this
is for fixtures that has been developed directly
for GrandMA 3 console there's a surprisingly
small number of fixtures in this pool and i would
expect this to grow a lot over the next few years
option three is GrandMA 2 this as the name
applies is the fixture library from the GrandMA
2 console it's a massive library that contains
a lot of fixture types and the cool thing is that
they can be patched directly on the GrandMA 3
console so if you can't find the fixture you need
in any of the other pools my guess is that you can
find it right here option 4 is the GDTF library
GDTF stands for general device type format GDTF
is some of the larger manufacturers ma lighting
vectorworks and robe they created this project
the general idea is that instead of all the
different manufacturers in the industry are having
to develop their own fixture profiles all the time
GDTF is supposed to be a standard where everybody
can make a fixture profile and you can use it
you can use the same profile across many of the
different platforms this means instead of having
vector works or MA lighting or cast soft to
develop a new fixture type profile for the
disk or software the manufacturer, ROBE, MARTIN,
Clay Packy or anyone else can make a fixture profile
for their brand new fixture and then it can be
implemented across different pieces of hardware
and software so hopefully when this really kicks
off there will be no more waiting for new fixtures
no matter if you need it for your 3d visualization
software or your lighting console i think
GDTF is a great idea and i really hope that
all manufacturers will start using it soon
this would make all our lives a lot easier in
the future i left a link to the GDTF website in
the description below here you can read much
more about gdtf and the thoughts behind it
next on the list is option 5 the user tab user
as the name indicates is where your own fixture
profiles are stored in the console if you make
your own fixture profile sometimes it can be
a little hard to find it again later on the
GrandMA 2 console but on the GrandMA 3 it's
stored right here directly in the user directory
last but not least is option 6 the shares tab
shares works if your console or on pc software
is connected to the internet shares will make
you search directly in a large online database and
here you can import the fixture you need directly
into your show this is a cool feature and this
will make your life as a programmer a lot easier
instead of having to go to a computer to find the
fixture you need and then saving it to a usb drive
for import you can do it directly on the console
itself so depending on what kind of fixture you
need in your show you can use the different
options here in the insert new fixture window
in the show we are starting up right
now we need four different fixture types
we need 12 pieces of martin mac viber profile
in the 16 bit version we need 12 pieces of
martin mac aura xp in standard mode we need six
pieces of martin atomic led in the extended mode
and last but not least we need 12 dimmer
channel for some 2 light blinders
you can always add more fixtures later in
the patch but this will just get us started
we will start in the GrandMA 2 library this
time for finding the fixture types for this show
so navigate to the GrandMA 2 tab and search
for Martin Mac viber profile click on the small
arrow icon and highlight martin Mac Viper profile
16-bit and press the select button in the bottom
of the window a new window appears with
four different lines you need to look at
the first line is what the console calls your
fixture after you have patched them you can leave
this line with whatever the console suggests but
i like to name it something that i can remember
so just type viper1 in the field if you
interline with a number the GrandMA 3
console will automatically increase it by +
1 on each fixture that will help you when you
look for the fixtures later in the fixture
window or in the 3d visualizer. the next line
quantity will tell the console how many Martin
Mac Viper profile you want to patch in your show
in this case we type 12 units the next line is the
fixture id for the Martin Mac Viper profile units
if you have never worked with a lighting console
before this might seem a little confusing but what
we do here is telling the console where you can
call these fixtures when you have patched them
it's best practice to have unique
numbers for every fixture in your patch
because it's very easy to call unit 712 or
unit 602 directly when you need it for some
reason i like my profile fixtures to be named
something with 700 i will type 701 in this field
this will now number all the mac viber
701 and forward in this case we have we
are patching 12 fixtures so my fixtures will be
701 through 7 12. the last line of this window
is the patch itself and it will tell the
console on what dmx universe and channel
you want to start the first of the 12 fixtures
in this case we start at universe 1 dmx channel
1. the GrandMA 3 console now starts with
the first address you told it to and then
automatically calculate the last addresses
based on how many channels each fixture uses
if you remember the last video where we looked
at the connections on the back of the console you
might remember we had output a b c d e and f if
you patch something on dmx universe 1 this is the
same dmx universe as number a or letter a on the
back this can easily be changed but that's for a
later tutorial in this case we keep the universe
and channel at 1.1 which means dmx universe 1
dmx channel 1. press apply and you now
have prepared your first 12 fixtures
i say prepared because we haven't patched anything
yet the patch is not active until you leave the
patch window and save your changes we will look at
that when we have patched all the fixtures we need
for the show to patch the rest of the fixtures
we need for this show repeat the process for
your Martin Mac Aura XB 16-bit fixtures search for
Aura XB expand the auras on the little arrow here
navigate to the standard rgb and press
select this time we name the units aura XB 1
in the first line we set the quantity to
12 units and we give it a fixture id of 601
this time we want the fixtures to be patched
to dmx universe 2 with a start address of 1 we
type 2.1 and press apply next up is the six Martin
ATOMIC fixtures navigate to new fixture search in
the GrandMA 2 library for atomic led locate the
atomic 3000 led extended version and press select
name it atomic 1 set a quantity of 6 set the
fixture id to 301 this time we will tries to
select the address in a different way most of the
time you'll be looking at a piece of paper with a
patch on it when you are patching your fixtures
but sometimes you don't have a patch sheet
this could be because it's a small show and
you just need to have new fixtures working fast
GrandMA 3 gives you a great overview on what
addresses that are available in the patch and
which dmx addresses you've already used on
other fixtures so instead of just typing the
universe an address this time we look at the
graphic overview if you click on the address
cell where it says 1.303 when you do that you are
presented with two options the calculator and the
sheet view if you click on the sheet tab you can
see a graphical overview of your dmx universes and
the addresses that are already occupied but some
of the fixtures we patched earlier in our show
right now it's showing us universe 1 but if you
want to select another dmx universe you can click
on the universe button up here in
the right corner of the sheet view
you can simply type the universe you want to
look at in this case we type 2 and the console
will show us universe 2. now you can scroll down
in the sheet until you find an empty address you
like it doesn't matter which address you choose
it all depends on what you want to do in your show
in this case it's 169 that are the first free dmx
address click on it and the view will jump back to
the first window with your choice of dmx universe
2 dmx address 169 press apply to lock down your
selection lastly we'll patch 12 dimmer channels
we need for our 12 pieces of two light blinders
right click on new fixture
choose the GrandMA 2 library
search for generic dimmer expand the dimmer
line click on dimmer and click select
name it dim 1 set the quantity of 12 type
the fixture id 101 and set the patch to 3.1
congratulations you have now patched all the
fixtures we need for this small demo show you
can now see the entire list of fixtures in your
patch if you scroll up and down in this list but
we have no grouping in order for this patch and
that can make it a little overwhelming if we have
to change something later this is where GrandMA 3 is a little different than GrandMA 2.
we have to manually add the group we want in our
show luckily it's quite easy once again navigate
to insert new fixture click on the GrandMA 3 tab
search for group and select the only option that
shows up here forget about the group name we'll
change that in a minute set the quantity to 4 and
forget the fixture id will also change that in a
minute click on the apply button you now have four
new empty lines in your patch window with wrong
numbers and wrong names let's change that quickly
if you look at the way we named and numbered
our fixtures we have mac viper 701 through 712
mac aura xp 601 through 612 martin atomics 301
through 312 and generic dimmer 101 through 112.
we named the four new groups like this the first
group is group 600 and we name it aura group
the second group is 700 and we name it viper
group the third group is group 300 and we name it
atomic group the last one is group 100 and we name
it dimmer group the group number will give you
quick access to the corresponding group
by just inputting the number for the group
the group numbers make it faster to select
a group in the future when we need it
although i'm not sure how much we're going
to use it actually because we'll make all our
groups another way in the next tutorial but let's
do this new way just to make sure we did it right
we now have named the four groups as we like
it but we still haven't moved any of the
corresponding fixtures into the right groups and
we'll do that right now mark all the martin mac
aura XB fixtures with your mouse or your finger
on the screen like this find the cut button below
in the patch window and click on it navigate to
your new aura group and click the little arrow
icon click on new fixture and click paste
side note you can click on the small paste
button but you can also use your keyboard
control plus v both works the same way
do the same for the other fixtures now all your
patching is done and we have separated it into
groups for a better overview of your patch sheet
the only thing that i left to do now is to close
the patch window you do that up here in the right
corner and you'll be prompted with three options
option two let's just start there discard an exit
if you think you made a mistake and you don't want
to save your changes option three stay in patch go
back to the patch to make more changes option one
save and exit in this case we're confident that we
did a good job and we'll just click save and exit
congratulations you have now patched
your first show on the GrandMA 3 console
we are now ready to start building our first
views and navigating around the console for real
if you get any value out of this video please
remember to like the video and subscribe to
the channel that would help us a lot and i
would like to hear from you in the comment
section if you have worked with GrandMA
consoles before or maybe you are a WholeHOG user
or Chamsys user and you're just looking to
learn GrandMA consoles for the first time
if you have any questions of any kind or maybe
you'd like to suggest other topics we should
cover in this series you are more than welcome
to leave a comment below as well next time
we'll start building the views we need to start
programming our show for real  - see you next time